Guide to the Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection 2010.020
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Burnett, Collette, 2010 May 10; 2010.020.008
  Collette Burnett was born in 1973 on Trinidad - the larger of two major islands which make up the island nation of Trinidad and Tobago - and immigrated to the United States in 1996. After initially living in Woodside, Queens, Burnett relocated to Crown Heights, Brooklyn to attend business school at Medgar Evers College. After working in finance as a small-business banker, Burnett was inspired to open her own restaurant. Her Caribbean-influenced eatery Super Wings was featured on a Food Network television show. In 2010, at the time of the interview, Burnett had been living in Crown Heights for nine years.
  Collette Burnett describes her first years in Crown Heights, Brooklyn as a business student at Medgar Evers College, as well as the reasoning behind her post-graduation plans to encourage a more proportionate share of Black-owned stores in the neighborhood. Burnett recounts how she first worked with small businesses as a banker, eventually opening her own Caribbean-inspired restaurant. She outlines her company philosophy regarding customer service and the reasoning behind her menu choices. The interview ends with Burnett offering some advice on hard work and perseverance, as well as an anecdote about her son. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Ansie Montilus, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Burnett, Collette; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College
- Burns, Louis, 2010 March 22; 2010.020.009
  Louis Burns was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1949. He grew up in Crown Heights, which he considers to have always been a close knit neighborhood of working class families. When he was younger, many of his friends and neighbors were of Irish descent and - as the postwar period of White flight progressed - increasingly of Puerto Rican heritage. After fathering a child at age sixteen, Burns left school to work and care for his daughter - although he would return in later years and eventually reach the post graduate level. In 2010 he was a consultant social worker, an adjunct professor of sociology and a proud grandfather. With the exception of eight years spent in Oneonta, New York, Burns has lived in Crown Heights his entire life.
  Louis Burns begins with his Brooklyn childhood in Crown Heights. He expounds on the day to day life of the neighborhood - including street games and other hijinks with his Irish and Puerto Rican friends - overseen by adult neighbors and teachers. Burns details his decision to drop out of high school as a teenage father, as well as his eventual return to school thanks to the help and encouragement of family and neighborhood elders. He describes the circumstances - namely the 1991 Crown Heights riot and 1995 Million Man March - surrounding his return after a move upstate to Oneonta, as well as his career as a social worker and college professor. Finally, Burns gives some pointers to the young interviewers regarding education, career, family and the company one keeps. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Quanaisha Phillips, Treverlyn Dehaarte, Floyya Richardson and Alex Kelly.
  Activists |z New York (State) |z New York; African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican families |z New York (State) |z New York; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Burns, Louis
- Caldwell, James E., 2010 April 8; 2010.020.010
  James Caldwell was born in Newbury County, South Carolina in 1951, the son of teenage sharecroppers. During his early years Caldwell was raised by an aunt in a rural setting while his parents tried to carve out a new life for the family in New York. While attending high school in Park Slope, Brooklyn, he worked as a grocery bagger as well as a bike messenger. After spending three years in Germany while in the Army, Caldwell began working as a car salesman - first in Texas and then back in Brooklyn, on Bensonhurst's 86th Street. After developing a reputation for being active in his home neighborhood of Crown Heights, Brooklyn, he was elected president of the 77th Precinct Community Council. A consistent presence in local politics, he also served as president of the non-profit Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (BUILD), which played a pivotal role in the construction of the Barclay's Center by endorsing builder Bruce Ratner's controversial development of Atlantic Yards.
  James Caldwell reminisces about an idyllic rural upbringing filled with tradition and superstition, as well as his first awed glimpse at the grand skyscrapers of New York. He recounts learning local geography and acquiring valuable social expertise during after-school jobs. Caldwell discusses his time in the Army, his youthful marriage to a member of the Women's Army Corps, as well as his triumphs and tribulations as a car salesman - including the different experiences of working as an outspoken young Black man in Texas and New York. He describes his career as a community activist - both as president of Crown Heights' 77th Precinct Council - as well as the president of Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (BUILD). He briefly touches on the controversy over BUILD's support for the construction of the Barclay's Center before offering some advice about focusing on one's goals. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Ansie Montilus and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barclays Center (New York, N.Y.); Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Farms; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); South Carolina; Texas; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Caldwell, James E.; United States. Army
- Camara, Karim, 2010 May 19; 2010.020.011
  Karim Camara was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1971. He spent his early childhood living in Crown Heights South on a diverse Brooklyn block of African American and Jewish families. After graduating college, Camara - who comes from a family of Christian ministers - decided to become a pastor as well as enter politics as state assemblyman for the 43rd district, representing his lifelong neighborhood. In February 2015, he vacated his seat to become executive director of the Office of Faith-Based Community Development as part of Governor Andrew Cuomo's administration. Camara holds a bachelor's degree in English Literature and Chemistry from Xavier University of Louisiana and a Masters of Divinity from the New York Theological Seminary.
  In the interview, Karim Camara offers interviewers biographical details - including the multifarious Crown Heights, Brooklyn of his childhood. He talks about what led him to the ministry, as well as the New York State Assembly. Camara discusses government funding, President Obama, his hectic dual work schedules and treating others with respect. He describes the homes and people who make up his district as well as his relations with constituents. Camara also goes over the difficulty of accurate census-taking and its importance in the allocation of tax dollars. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Census; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State); Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fundraising |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Municipal government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); New York (State) |x Politics and government; Camara, Karim; Obama, Barack
- Copeland, Londell, 2010 March 23; 2010.020.012
  Londell Copeland was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1978. He grew up in Crown Heights, Brooklyn - the child of a single mother. With little parental guidance, he spent much of his childhood socializing in the environment of the streets, where an outlaw morality prevailed. Often a discipline problem at school, Copeland lived in several group homes. He eventually ran into trouble with the law, squandering several years in prison. Upon release, Copeland opted to turn his anguished life around; marrying a childhood sweetheart, returning to school and participating in job training programs. At the time of the interview in 2010, he was a proud father living in Starrett City - an apartment complex in eastern Brooklyn - with his wife and son.
  Londell Copeland opens up about his childhood in a broken, neglectful home, juvenile delinquency and later troubles with the law. Happier subjects, such as his current family, are touched on along with expressions of hope for the future. He elaborates on what life is like for a convicted felon; including education and job training. A proud husband and father, Copeland explains how his son exemplifies some of his own better qualities, as well as how his wife and son help to fortify him with the courage to carry on. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ex-convicts |x Rehabilitation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Juvenile delinquency |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Copeland, Londell; Starrett City (Housing complex)
- Corney, Janel, 2010 April 19; 2010.020.013
  Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
  Corney, Janel
- Edmund, Evelyn, 2010 April 28; 2010.020.014
  Evelyn Edmund was born in New York City in 1934, the child of Guyanese immigrants. Growing up in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, she excelled in school and was active in a number of academic and youth organizations. Edmund and her husband moved as newlyweds from East New York - which was quickly deteriorating due to crime - to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in June of 1961. Together, they raised three children and remained active in both their children's education, as well as neighborhood affairs. A health care administrator, she was employed for a time at Long Island College Hospital and subsequently worked as office manager in a private psychiatric practice.
  Evelyn Edmund describes her experiences as both a bright, ambitious child and civic-minded adult. She recounts happy memories growing up in an upwardly mobile East New York, Brooklyn and the encroaching urban blight which prompted her and her husband to settle in the Crown Heights section in 1961. Edmund speaks about the ebb and flow of crime and poverty - as well as money and gentrification - over decades punctuated by significant historic events including wars, assassinations and riots. She also weighs the pros and cons of recent trends in parenting and adult-child relations against those of her own youth. The process of change in local politics - particularly regarding neighborhood schools - are also discussed at length. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Edmund, Evelyn
- Elliott, Zetta, 2010 March 24; 2010.020.015
  Zetta Elliott was born in 1972 and raised in Canada. She made her first visit to New York City and to her cousin Lil's home in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1979. Elliott moved to Brooklyn in 1994 and has been a permanent United States resident since the late 1990s. She received a doctoral degree in American Studies from New York University in 2003. She is a poet, playwright, essayist, author, blogger and publisher. Her award-winning books include the picture book, "Bird," and the novel "Ship of Souls." "The Deep" was published in 2013. In 2015, she was the writer-in-residence at the Weeksville Heritage Center. A self-described Black feminist writer committed to social justice, Elliott continues to live in Brooklyn.
  In the interview, Zetta Elliott recalls her first memories of New York City in 1979 and her cousin Lil's house on Eastern Parkway in Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood. She touches on her grandfather's history in Antigua and Canada and how her cousin made money from selling crocheted items at a hospital. Elliott discusses going to graduate school at New York University and becoming an author, listing her books that take place in Brooklyn. She notes the importance of "mapping community" and appreciating local landmarks and architecture. She discusses her father's immigration from the Caribbean to Canada and the United States as well as her own immigration to New York City. She describes her mother, mentioning a brief genealogy that included slavery. Elliott closes by advising on the importance of listening to peoples' stories. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Canada; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York; Libraries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Women authors, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Children's Museum; Brooklyn Public Library; Elliott, Zetta; New York University
- Empty, Dollmarie, 2010 March 22; 2010.020.016
  Born in Jamaica in 1971, Dollmarie Empty moved in with her mother in Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood circa 1995. She worked as a nanny, housekeeper and home health aide before having to collect on Social Security for a disability in the years prior to this 2010 interview. She did not graduate high school but was preparing to get her certificate of General Educational Development (GED) at the time of the interview.
  In the interview, Dollmarie Empty contrasts the culture of her homeland of Jamaica with the cultural diversity of Brooklyn. She evaluates the restaurant options and new foods she has encountered in the neighborhood of Crown Heights. Empty envisions her future and contemplates getting a General Educational Development (GED) certificate. In closing, she makes observations about a few changes in the neighborhood. This interview was conducted by Alex Kelly and abbreviated due to technical difficulties.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn Public Library; Empty, Dollmarie
- Esquilin, Frank, 2010 April 26; 2010.020.017
  Born in New York City in 1947, Frank Esquilin was raised in the Harlem section of Manhattan. A high school dropout, Esquilin was a technician for Verizon and its predecessor companies for thirty-two years. He is a father of four and shared the responsibilities of raising his family for some time in Brooklyn's Ozone Park neighborhood. With the last of his children becoming adults, he moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the mid-1990s. He retired in 2004 with a pension and, due to his love of books and advice from his mother, took to creating craft book covers and wallets. He often sells his wares at the Franklin Avenue Flea Market in Crown Heights. In 2013, he helped to establish a sewing scholarship for select high school students to study under a master tailor. In 2014, Esquilin became the President of the Crow Hill Community Association, taking the reins from founder Eve Porter.
  Frank Esquilin begins the interview by tracing his background from Harlem in Manhattan to the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Ozone Park and Crown Heights. Esquilin describes his entry into crafting, in particular his book protectors and wallets. Traveling has featured greatly in his retirement and he speaks about the special places he's visited and the perception of Americans in those countries. Esquilin recalls his work experience at the phone company after dropping out of high school. He talks at length about the changes in Crown Heights over the past fifteen years, including the increased presence of police officers, patterns of garbage and recycling pick-up, local businesses, rent changes for residents and other developments on Franklin Avenue. (Esquilin notes the appearance of Kevin Phillip, another narrator in this oral history collection.) He recounts his understanding of what led up to the 1991 riot in the neighborhood. In closing, he remarks on the evolution of terminology like "ghetto" and "inner city" and how renaming neighborhoods is a marketing tool in the real estate business. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African Americans |x Relations with Jews; African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Multiculturalism; Ozone Park (New York, N.Y.); Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cato, Gavin; Esquilin, Frank; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Rosenbaum, Yankel; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
- Fawundu-Buford, Delphine, 2010 May 4; 2010.020.018
  Delphine Fawundu was born on Brooklyn's Eastern Parkway in 1971, and was primarily raised on Carroll Street and at Tivoli Towers, both in the Crown Heights neighborhood. She participated in a building-sponsored track team as a child and attended P.S. 241 and I.S. 320 in Brooklyn. She has a master's degree in Media Ecology from New York University, a master's degree from Mercy College and a bachelor's degree from the state school at Stony Brook. Fawundu grew up with two siblings in her mother's home. She has three sons with Howard Buford. Fawundu is a photographer, with professional experience dating back to the early 1990s, and an educator. In 2010, she produced a documentary short, "Tivoli: A Place We Call Home," and exhibited related photographs at Brooklyn Historical Society. Her work is also in the collection of the Brooklyn Museum of Art, among many others. She has received a number of fellowships, grants and residencies, and creates in locations all over the world.
  In the interview, Delphine Fawundu talks about her family's moves within Brooklyn and becoming part of the community of Tivoli Towers in the neighborhood of Crown Heights, noting that she lives there as an adult and raises her family there. She speaks at length about gentrification and its subtle and overt effects on Tivoli Towers and about the documentary she created concerning that subject. She observes the changes that have occurred in Crown Heights over decades and discusses her sense of personal safety in the neighborhood. She reminisces about West Indian Carnival in her childhood and favorite personal and community traditions. Fawundu recalls her enjoyment of elementary school and playing with other children at the towers. She describes married life and the moment she knew she was a photographer. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Carroll Street (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Photographers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Botanic Garden; Fawundu, Delphine; Tivoli Towers (Brooklyn, N.Y.); West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Green, Pamela, 2010 May 26; 2010.020.019